Guide to the William J. Gaughan Collection, 1887-2000 (Bulk 1940-1980) AIS.1994.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Motion Picture Films, ca. 1956-ca. 1974; XI.
  - The Carban: Oxygen Reaction in the Open Hearth Bath, Quality Series c-1, c-2 Metallurgical Process Control; Copyright 1957, United States Steel Corporation; 16mm, B&W, optical audio; 800 feet (Oversize 26, Reel 22)
  - Where's Joe?, Cinecraft Inc., 1972; Sponsored by United States Steel Workers of American and the Coordinating Committee Steel Companies; 16mm, color, optical audio; 900 feet (Oversize 26, Reel 23)
  - Untitled Training Film, 16mm, B&W, optical audio (Oversize 26, Reel 24)
  - Last Rolling at 48" Mill (12-29-1979) and Last Heat at OH 5 (6-23-1982), 1979-1982 (Oversize 26, Reel 25)
    16mm film footage documenting the last steel rolled at the 48" mill and the last heat at O.H. #5. Approximately 10 minutes.
- Oversize Prints, Architectural Drawings, Blueprints, and Miscellaneous, ca. 1890-ca. 1970; XII.
  Among the items in this series are drawings of mill equipment and plans showing mill properties. Oversize prints of panoramic views of the mills and ephemera are also included.
  - Architectural Drawings and Blue Prints, 1.
    - 60 ton rope power traveling crane, May 1891 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item AA #68)
    - Shafting for driving cranes in press shop- Homestead Steel Works, June 1, 1891 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item AA #88)
    - Arrangement for driving cranes in new armor plate machine shop - Homestead Steel Works, June 13, 1891 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item AA #93)
    - 60 ton power traveling crane. Tracing No. 70N, Craven Bros. Ltd. Traced from print, August 7, 1891 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item AA #148)
    - Dies for 2,000 ton hydraulic press for gun sponsors of "New York", May 24, 1892 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item AA #239)
    - Building plan and section S.T.S. Treating Shop, Heat Treating Department, October 7, 1940 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item AA #3876)
    - Map, corrected borough line- Borough of Rankin Station (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item AH Sheet 119)
    - Map of property belonging to the Carrie Furnace Co. Situated at Kroling Station, the Borough of Rankin, September 1894 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item AH Sheet 200)
    - Foundation of 48" universal mill--Homestead Steel Works [poor condition], November 16, 1892 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item AK #163)
    - Foundation for 48" universal mill--Homestead Steel Works [poor condition], November 17, 1898 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item AK #164)
    - Foundations for 50" x 60" reversing engines-48" universal mill--Homestead Steel Works [poor condition], December 7, 1898 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item AK #190)
    - Arrangement to bring outlet of 119" mill sewer 180 ft. below intake to pump house. Carnegie Steel Co., Homestead Works [poor condition], October 5, 1901 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Images C.E. 2)
    - Map showing main line and branch line of the Union R.R. through the Homestead Steel Mills, September 1896 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 5)
    - Section of Test Wells Homestead Steel Works. Carnegie Steel Co. [2 copies, C.E. 66 is located in same file], July 13, 1904 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 53a)
    - Section of Test Wells, Number 3. Homestead Steel Works [2 copies], March 13, 1905 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 53b)
    - Section of test wells on the Denniston property, Carnegie Steel Co. Carrie Furnaces [2 copies, located in same file as C.E. 53a], December 29, 1905 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 66)
    - Water lines at A.P. Department and 35"-40" Mills--Homestead Steel Works, January 20, 1914 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 177)
    - Plan of property of PBG Bessemer Steel Works Limited, December 1879 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 240)
    - Homestead- Carrie Furnaces, Briquette. Central Dock, Wheel and Axle Division, rev. March 1956 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 3683)
    - Homestead and Carrie Furnaces--U.S.S. Corp, April 28, 1976 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 3683-P)
    - Hydraulic lines, Homestead (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 3698)
    - Proposed location of pumping station, setting basins, and trunk water lines--Homestead Steel Works, March 21, 1919 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 4007)
    - Duplicate (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 4007)
    - Mill Diagram [Superseded by C.E. 3647] (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item C.E. 4010)
    - General plan of Homestead Steel Works; Howard Axle Works, Hays Yard Construction program of 1931-revised [2 copies] (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item EXH 34)
    - General plan of Armor Plate Department- Homestead Steel Works, November 1, 1904 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item F1 #1533)
    - Piston Rod for Blacksmiths Shop--Pittsburgh Bessemer Steel Co. Ltd, May 15, 1882 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item G #24)
    - Plan showing part of Carnegie Steel Company's Property--Homestead Steel Works, April 27, 1908 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item G 393)
    - Steel for pouring car; New converting mill--Homestead Steel Works, August 25, 1892 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item G 1024)
    - General Plan, East of City Farm Lane, Building and Equipment--Homestead Steel Works, 1923 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item G 1554)
    - Plan of buildings--Homestead Steel Works [2 copies], August 13, 1906 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item G 1816)
    - Details for Intermediate Building--Carnegie, Phipps and Co. Ltd, July 1, 1886 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item I #73)
    - General Plan of 72" and 84" plate mills--Carnegie Steel Co. Homestead Steel Works [2 copies] (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item I 1044)
    - General plan of 34" and 72" plate mills, and Open Hearth No. 1--Carnegie Steel Co. Homestead Steel Works [2 copies] (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item I 1400)
    - Mill diagram [2 copies], April 21, 1927 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item I 1400a)
    - Plan of lot residence of C.M. Schwab; Munhall, PA, September 17, 1896 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item K 54)
    - First Floor plan; General Superintendent's Residence [2 copies], May 17, 1919 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item K 505)
    - Second floor plan; General Superintendent's Residence. Carnegie Steel Co. Homestead Steel Works [2 copies], May 17, 1919 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item K 506)
    - Third floor plan; General Superintendent's Residence. Carnegie Steel Co. Homestead Steel Works [2 copies], May 20, 1919 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item K 507)
    - Plan of shrubbery beds and trees; Residence of General Superintendent--Homestead Steel Works [2 copies], January 18, 1921 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item K 540)
    - Space Diagrams for Carnegie Library, Homestead (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item K 856)
    - Plan of 100" plate mill and 45" slabbing mill [2 copies] (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item PD 216)
    - Plan of 160" plate mill (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item PD 218)
    - Plan of forgings division [2 copies] (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item PD 219)
    - Details of water tank for new waterworks at Homestead Steel Works, May 10, 1888 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item R Imp 39A)
    - Water Works; Carnegie Steel Co, Homestead Steel Works, March 26, 1923 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item R 147)
    - Arrangement of 40-0 tank and piping for waterworks. Carnegie Steel Co, Homestead Steel Works, April 11, 1912 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item R 168)
    - General plan of open hearth basic plant; Homestead Steel Works [2 copies], June 1890 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item T #183)
    - General plan of open hearth basic plan; Homestead Steel Works [2 copies], June 1890 (Map-case 12, Drawer 1-3, Item T #185)
  - Folio Sized Prints, 2.
    - Photographic Panoramic Print of Edgar Thomson Works [very fragile], 1. (Map-case 12, Drawer 4)
    - Photographic Panoramic Print of Edgar Thomson Works, June 11, 1927; 2.
    - View of mill from above the river, 3.
    - Large gathering/party [very fragile], 4.
    - Department Superintendent's Club of Homestead Steel Works, April 30, 1914; 5.
    - Department Superintendent's Club of Edgar Thomson Works, 1909; 6.
    - J. Edgar Thomson, etching, 7.
    - J. Edgar Thomson, photographic print, 8.
    - S.S. Santa Paula, 1932; 9.
    - Anti-Communist Proclamation signed by employees of Carnegie Illinois Steel Corporation, 10.
    - Panoramic shot of Homestead Works, 1906; 11.
  - Miscellaneous, 3.
    - Drawing of Homestead, PA, 1902 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 1)
    - Map of Braddock and North Braddock showing the location of the field of Battle, July 9, 1755. Based upon maps made by Pat Mackeller, Engineer with Braddock's army (battle located by Sydney Dillon, Chief Engineer at Edgar Thomson Works), undated (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 2)
    - U.S.S. Corporation; Homestead District Works, 1965 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 3)
    - U.S.S. Homestead Steel Works Press Shop No. 1; History and diagram (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 4)
    - Press Shop No. 1 (Architectural Diagram), showing expansions in 1891, 1893, and 1903, 1989 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 5)
    - Press Shop No. 1; Architectural diagrams, 1891 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 6)
    - Plan of Press Shop No. 1, 1891 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 7)
    - Partial plan of Press Shop No. 1, 1893 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 8)
    - Addition to Press Shop No.1, 1903 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 9)
    - Partial plan of Press Shop No. 1, 1903 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 10)
    - Section A-A through Press Shop No. 1, 1903 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 11)
    - 12,000 ton press, 1903 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 12)
    - Bethlehem Press (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 13)
    - Balance accumulator, 1903 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 14)
    - Plan, Edgar Thomson Works (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 15)
    - Calendar; United States Steel, 1978 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 16)
    - Carnegie Steel Co, Homestead Steel Works. Map of Homestead Borough, March 12, 1920 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 17)
    - Drawing of Homestead, PA [2 copies], 1902 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 18)
    - Map of Munhall, Homestead and West Homestead, undated (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 19)
    - Homestead Works Organization Charts, 1970 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 20-32)
    - The Veteran's Employees Association of the Edgar Thomson Works, Citizenship Certification for Brindle, 1938 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 33)
    - U.S.S 1927 Calendar (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 34)
    - Rhapsody of Steel LP Record (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 35)
    - Pittsburgh Sun Telegraph Newspaper August 1945 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 36)
    - Copy of Congressional Record/House of Reps. U.S.S Enters Second Century. Hon. Joseph M. Gaydos, May 7, 1981 (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 37)
    - Copy of print from L'Encyclopedie de Science, des Arts et des Metiers par Denis Diderot, 1752, depicting open hearth steel-making (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 38)
    - Print entitled "Heating" (Map-case 12, Drawer 2, Item 39)
  - Bound Materials, Binders, and Publications, 4.
    - Out of This Furnace by Thomas Bell, 1976 (Box 28, Item 1)
    - Metallurgy for Engineers:Casting, Welding, and Working by John Wulff, Howard F. Taylor, and Amos J. Shaler, 1956 (Box 28, Item 2)
    - Textbook of Quantitative Inorganic Analysis by I.M. Kolthoff, and E. B. Sandell, 1945 (Box 28, Item 3)
    - A Western Journal by Thomas Wolfe, 1951 (Box 28, Item 4)
    - Canal History and Technology Proceedings Volume XI Edited by Lance E. Metz, March 14, 1992 (Box 28, Item 5)
    - Basic Open Hearth Steelmaking by the Physical Chemistry of Steelmaking Committee, 1951 (Box 28, Item 6)
    - Metals Handbook published by American Society for Metals, 1939 (Box 28, Item 7)
    - Engineering Metals and Their Alloys by Carl H. Samans, 1949 (Box 28, Item 8)
    - Pocket Companion: For Engineers, Architects and Builders by Carnegie Steel Company, 1923 (Box 28, Item 9)
    - Carnegie Shape Book: Profiles, Tables, and Data for Rolled Products by Carnegie Steel Company, 1929 (Box 28, Item 10)
    - Pocket Companion by United States Steel, 1936 (Box 28, Item 11)
    - The Making, Shaping and Treating of Steel by Carnegie Steel Company, 1925 (Box 28, Item 13)
    - The Making, Shaping and Treating of Steel by Carnegie Steel Company, 1920 (Box 28, Item 12)
    - Steel by David Plowden, 1981 (Box 29, Item 1)
    - Biography of a Business, 1960 (Box 29, Item 2)
    - Pittsburgh: The Story of a City 1750-1865 by Leland D. Baldwin, 1981 (Box 29, Item 3)
    - Iron Pioneer: Henry W. Oliver 1840-1904 by Henry Oliver Evans, 1942 (Box 29, Item 4)
    - Steel Titan: The Life of Charles M. Schwab by Robert Hessen, 1975 (Box 29, Item 5)
    - Andrew Carnegie by Joseph Frazier Wall, 1970 (Box 29, Item 6)
    - Henry Clay Frick: The Man by George Harvey, 1928 (Box 29, Item 7)
    - Pittsburgh edited by Roy Lubove, 1976 (Box 29, Item 8)
    - The Battle for Homestead 1880-1892: Politics, Culture, and Steel by Paul Krause, 1992 (Box 29, Item 9)
    - The Homestead Strike of 1892 by Arthur G. Burgoyne, 1979 (Box 29, Item 10)
    - Lockout by Leon Wolff, 1965 (Box 29, Item 11)
    - Homestead: The Glory and Tragedy of An American Steel Town by William Serrin, 1992 (Box 29, Item 12)
    - Watkins Cyclopedia of the Steel Industry published by Steel Publications, INC., 1949 (Box 29, Item 13)
    - Watkins Cyclopedia of the Steel Industry published by Steel Publications, INC., 1971 (Box 29, Item 14)
    - Metallurgical Formulas specific to U.S. Steel, 1967-1978 (Box 30, Item 1)
    - The Steel Workers by John A. Fitch, 1989 (Box 30, Item 2)
    - Rusted Dreams: Hard Times in a Steel Community by David Bensman and Roberta Lynch, 1988 (Box 30, Item 3)
    - Development of the American Tin Plate Industry by United States Steel (Box 30, Item 4)
    - Sparrows Point by Mark Reutter, 1988 (Box 30, Item 5)
    - The Decline of American Steel by Paul A. Tiffany, 1988 (Box 30, Item 6)
    - The Corporation: A Centennial Biography of United States Steel Corporation, 1901-2001 by Brian Apelt, 2000 (Box 30, Item 7)
    - U.S.S. Structural Sections, 1940 (Box 30, Item 8)
    - Atlas of Isothermal Transformation Diagrams by United States Steel, 1951 (Box 30, Item 9)
    - Cloud By Day by Muriel Earley Sheppard, 1975 (Box 30, Item 10)
    - United States Steel: A Corporation with a Soul by Arundel Cotter, 1921 (Box 30, Item 11)
    - Triumphant Democracy by Andrew Carnegie, 1886 (Box 30, Item 12)
    - History of Carnegie Veteran Association, 1938 (Box 30, Item 13)
    - The Inside History of the Carnegie Steel Company by James Howard Bridge, 1903 (Box 30, Item 14)
    - Organization Manual Heavy Products Operations Homestead Works by United States Steel Corporation, 1967 (Box 30, Item 15)
    - Historic Bridges of Pennsylvania by William H. Shank, 1986 (Box 30, Item 16)
    - Photocopy of Organizational Manual Heavy Products Operations Homestead Works, December 1, 1966 (Box 30, Item 17)
    - The Edgar Thomson Steel Works and Blast Furnaces, 1890 (Box 31, Item 1)
    - Carnegie Veteran Association, 1905 (Box 31, Item 2)
    - Facts About Pittsburgh Andrew Carnegie Booklet, 1902-1904 (Box 31, Item 3)
      The outside cover of the booklet holds a delicate picture of Andrew Carnegie.
    - U.S.S. Administrative Directory Pittsburgh District, October, 1953 (Box 31, Item 4)
    - U.S.S. Administrative Directory Pittsburgh Distric, November 1959 (Box 31, Item 5)
    - Homestead Works Telephone Directory, 1975 (Box 31, Item 6)
    - Homestead Works Telephone Directory, 1980 (Box 31, Item 7)
    - Steel Plant Design Rolling Mills Vol.I for the Carnegie-Illinois Steel Corporation, 1945 (Box 31, Item 8)
    - Steel Plant Design Rolling Mills Vol.II for Carnegie-Illinois Steel Corporation, 1945 (Box 31, Item 9)
    - Steel Plant Design Rolling Mills Vol.III for Carnegie-Illinois Steel Corporation, 1945 (Box 31, Item 10)
    - This is Steel by United States Steel Corporation (Box 32, Item 1)
    - The Manufacture and Properties of Iron and Steel by Harry Campbell, 1907 (Box 32, Item 2)
    - Romancing in Tin Plate by Roy Rutherford, 1951 (Box 32, Item 3)
    - The Making, Shaping and Treating of Steel 8th Edition by United States Steel, 1964 (Box 32, Item 4)
    - The Making, Shaping and Treating of Steel 7th edition by United States Steel, 1957 (Box 32, Item 5)
    - Steel Serves the Nation by United States Steel, 1951 (Box 32, Item 6)
    - The Making of Steel by American Iron and Steel Institute, 1964 (Box 32, Item 7)
    - From Fire to Rust by Thomas E. Leary and Elizabeth C. Sholes, 1987 (Box 32, Item 8)
    - One Billion Dollars in Progress, ca. 1964 (Box 32, Item 9)
    - Romance of Steel Information Pamphlets, 1956-1961 (Box 32, Folder 1, Item 10-14)
    - United States Steel Company Pamphlets, 1961-1970 (Box 32, Folder 2, Item 13-18)
    - United States Steel Coporation Annual Report, 1966 (Box 32, Folder 3, Item 19)
    - Carnegie Works Essay by Theodore Dreiser, 1980 (Box 32, Folder 4, Item 20)
    - Iron Age Magazines, 1976-1980 (Box 32, Folder 5, Item 21-22)
    - Pittsburgh Magazine, June 1992 (Box 32, Folder 6, Item 23)
    - Art Catalog, 1986-1987 (Box 32, Folder 7, Item 24)
    - Furnace Poetry, 1993 (Box 32, Folder 8, Item 25)
- Ephemera, XIII.
  This series contains materials that were added to the collection in 2012. This addition consists of badges, buttons, various United States Steel promotional items, metal samples, items used by Gaughan in the course of his employment, and books detailing the United State Steel the Homestead Strike. Also included are two Carnegie Steel Police badges.
  - Ephemera (Box 33-34, 36-39)
- Personal, XIV.
  The Personal series consists of items used for research and projects as well as correspondence and other papers of interest.
  - Correspondence (Box 40, Folder 17-25)
    Correspondence relating to William J. Gaughan's contributions of photographs or expertise in publications.
  - Trail Marker Homestead, 1999 (Box 40, Folder 26)
  - Braddock's Crossing Trail and War (Box 40, Folder 27)
  - Boy Scouts (Box 40, Folder 28)
  - Research Materials on William Dickson (Box 40, Folder 29-30)
  - Personnel File, 1962-1983 (Box 40, Folder 32)
    Personnell file providing a history of William J. Gaughan's duties within United States Steel Corporation.
  - From Mill Town to Mall: Blue Collar Transformation in Pittsburgh's Turtle Creek Valley- Proposal (Box 40, Folder 34)